Register of the Mary Catherine Roberts Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Mary Catherine Roberts papers
1918-1978
2001C37
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Correspondence, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to American Red Cross relief work in Siberia during the Russian Civil War.
Roberts, Mary Catherine, 1884-1978
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Mary Roberts was born in England on 8 October 1884, trained there as a nurse, and subsequently emigrated to the United States. During the First World War, she joined the army medical services, and was sent to Siberia to serve with the American Red Cross in May 1919.
The materials in her collection reflect her service in Vladivostok and include clippings, correspondence, bulletins and other material pertaining to Red Cross and YMCA work in Siberia in 1919-1920. Some of her letters and reports were published in the Washington state press.
Following her return to the United States in 1920, she received a degree in public health from the University of Washington, and worked as a school nurse in Yakima county, Washington. She retired in 1960 and moved to Seattle, where she died on 3 June 1978.
Chronology
1884 (?) Born, England
1919-1920 Nurse, Siberian Commission of the American Red Cross
? Received a degree in public health form the University of Washington County school nurse in Yakima
1960 Retired and returned to Seattle
1978 Died, Seattle
Scope and Content Note
Mary Catherine Roberts was a nurse with the Siberian Commission of the American Red Cross in 1919-1920. She spent several months in Vladivostok and Irkutsk, where the Red Cross gave relief to Russian refugees. This collection contains clippings about the activities of the American Red Cross in Siberia, the evacuation of Russian children from Vladivostok to Petrograd in 1920-1921, the execution of the Czar's family, and several issues of The Siberian See-Chas, a bulletin for the Members of the American Expeditionary Force in Siberia.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
American National Red Cross.; International relief.; Russia (Federation); Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Civilian relief.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations.
- Biographical File, 1919-1978 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Scrapbook containing M. C. Roberts's passport, clippings about her and her work, and bulletins, and miscellany
- Correspondence, 1918-1958 (Box 1)
  A telegram to M. C. Roberts from the American Red Cross and letters from Riley H. Allen and unidentified person
- Clippings, 1919-1974 (Box 1)
  Clippings on the Red Cross evacuation of Russian children from Vladivostok to Petrograd in 1920-1921 and about Riley H. Allen, secretary of the Siberian Commission of the American Red Cross
- Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  Three prints depicting M. C. Roberts, Dr. C. F. Reppun with family, and city of Irkutsk; album of prints taken by war correspondents and collected by a member of the American Expeditionary Forces in Siberia, depicting Red Cross personnel, Czechoslovak Legion in Siberia, General Horvat, General Gaida's insurrection, Admiral Kolchak, the Bolshevik army, and Allied Expeditionary Forces in Siberia. Includes correspondence between Alexander M. Poniatoff and Gertrude Batchelder
- Memorabilia, n.d. (Box 1)
  Five Red Cross pins
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1919-1978 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes passport and clippings about M. C. Roberts, activities of the American Red Cross in Siberia, execution of the Czar's family, several issues of The Siberian See-Chas, a bulletin for the Members of the American Expeditionary Force in Siberia and The American Red Cross, the Siberian Commission bulletin, reports about the evacuation of the American Red Cross from Omsk
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1918-1958 (Folder 1: 3)
  General note
  See also PHOTOGRAPHS
  A telegram to M. C. Roberts from the American Red Cross and letters from Riley H. Allen and unidentified person.
- CLIPPINGS, 1919-1974 (Folder 1: 4)
  Clippings on the Red Cross evacuation of Russian children from Vladivostok to Petrograd in 1920-1921. Also includes clippings about Riley H. Allen, secretary of the Siberian Commission of the American Red Cross
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d.
  - Three prints depicting M. C. Roberts, Dr. C. F. Reppun with family, and the city of Irkutsk (Folder 1: 5)
  - Album of pictures taken by war correspondents and collected by a member of the American Expeditionary Forces in Siberia, depicting Red Cross personnel, Czechoslovak Legion in Siberia, General Horvat, General Gaida's insurrection, Admiral Kolchak, the Bolshevik army, and Allied Expeditionary Forces in Siberia. (Folder 1: 6)
    Also includes correspondence between Alexander M. Poniatoff and Gertrude Batchelder
- MEMORABILIA, n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
  Consists of five Red Cross pins